<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>configurable products Archives - Rutvik Bhatt</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description>Technologist and Engineering Leader</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 22:37:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://i0.wp.com/rutvikbhatt.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-Rbg-favicon.png?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>configurable products Archives - Rutvik Bhatt</title>
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">178776205</site>	<item>
		<title>Configurability in Product Development: A Guide for Engineering Leaders</title>
		<link>./../../../configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/index.html?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders</link>
					<comments>./../../../configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rutvik Bhatt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 21:48:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Software Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[configurable products]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[flexibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[time to market]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../embracing-configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/index.html</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the fast-paced world of software development, the ability to adapt and customize products to meet unique customer needs is increasingly vital. However, building configurable products might not always be the first choice for product managers who lean towards standardized solutions. As an engineering leader, it&#8217;s essential to understand why configurability matters and how you...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/index.html">Configurability in Product Development: A Guide for Engineering Leaders</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Rutvik Bhatt</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the fast-paced world of software development, the ability to adapt and customize products to meet unique customer needs is increasingly vital. However, building configurable products might not always be the first choice for product managers who lean towards standardized solutions. As an engineering leader, it&#8217;s essential to understand why configurability matters and how you can shift your team&#8217;s mindset to embrace it, even when your product managers may be hesitant. In this post, we&#8217;ll explore the what, why, and how of building configurable products.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Why Build Configurable Products?</h3>



<p>Before delving into the &#8220;how,&#8221; let&#8217;s first address the &#8220;why&#8221; behind building configurable products. There are several compelling reasons to consider:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Customer-Centric Approach:</strong> Configurable products empower customers to tailor software to their specific needs. This level of customization can lead to increased customer satisfaction and loyalty.</li>



<li><strong>Market Adaptability:</strong> In rapidly changing markets, configurable products can be quickly adjusted to respond to new trends, competitors, or emerging customer demands, giving your company a competitive edge.</li>



<li><strong>Reduced Development Time:</strong> While it may seem counterintuitive, building configurable products can streamline development. Once the framework is in place, creating new configurations is often faster than building entirely new products from scratch.</li>



<li><strong>Cost Efficiency:</strong> Configurable products can result in cost savings by reducing the need for extensive development of niche, one-off solutions.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Shifting Left: Changing Mindsets</h3>



<p>Shifting your team&#8217;s mindset towards building configurable products can be a challenge, especially if your product managers are initially resistant. Here are some strategies to help you navigate this shift:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Educate Your Team:</strong> Host workshops or training sessions to help your team understand the benefits of configurability. Use real-world examples of successful configurable products to illustrate the impact.</li>



<li><strong>Collaborate Closely:</strong> Work closely with your product managers to find common ground. Encourage open communication and align on the long-term goals of configurability.</li>



<li><strong>Start Small:</strong> Begin by identifying one or two features that could benefit from configurability. Pilot these within your team to demonstrate the advantages.</li>



<li><strong>Showcase Success Stories:</strong> Share success stories from other companies that have embraced configurability, highlighting the positive outcomes.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How to Build Configurable Products</h3>



<p>Now that you&#8217;re convinced of the benefits and have started shifting your team&#8217;s mindset, let&#8217;s dive into how to build configurable products effectively:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Modular Architecture:</strong> Design your software with modularity in mind. Break down complex systems into smaller, interchangeable components that can be easily configured.</li>



<li><strong>User-Friendly Configuration Interfaces:</strong> Invest in creating intuitive user interfaces for configuring the product. Ensure that customers can customize without needing a technical background.</li>



<li><strong>Testing and Quality Assurance:</strong> Rigorously test all possible configurations to ensure stability and avoid unexpected issues. Automation can be invaluable for this step.</li>



<li><strong>Documentation:</strong> Provide comprehensive documentation and support resources to guide users through the configuration process.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Leveraging Feature Flagging and YAML/JSON Tooling</h3>



<p>When building configurable products, one powerful approach is to incorporate feature flagging alongside YAML or JSON tooling. This combination can help you efficiently manage configurations for each modular nano component of your architecture and product features.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Feature Flagging</h4>



<p>Feature flagging, also known as feature toggles or feature switches, is a development technique that allows you to turn specific product features on or off at runtime. Here&#8217;s how it can benefit your configurable product:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Gradual Rollouts:</strong> Feature flags enable you to roll out new configurations gradually. You can initially deploy a feature to a small subset of users, gather feedback, and make adjustments as needed before a broader release.</li>



<li><strong>Emergency Rollbacks:</strong> In case of unexpected issues with a new configuration, you can quickly roll back to a previous state by toggling off the feature flag, minimizing downtime and user impact.</li>



<li><strong>A/B Testing:</strong> You can use feature flags for A/B testing to compare the performance and user experience of different configurations and make data-driven decisions.</li>



<li><strong>Conditional Logic:</strong> Implement complex configuration logic within your codebase using feature flags. This allows for dynamic customization based on user profiles, groups, or specific conditions.</li>
</ol>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><a href="https://yaml.org/">YAML</a> or <a href="https://www.json.org/json-en.html">JSON</a> Tooling</h4>



<p>To complement feature flagging, YAML or JSON configuration files can store and manage the various settings and options for your modular nano components. Here&#8217;s how YAML or JSON can enhance your configurability:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Human-Readable:</strong> YAML and JSON are both human-readable formats, making it easier for developers and product managers to understand and modify configurations without diving deep into code.</li>



<li><strong>Version Control:</strong> Configuration files can be version-controlled alongside your codebase, ensuring that changes are tracked, documented, and auditable.</li>



<li><strong>Portability:</strong> These formats are portable across different programming languages and platforms, allowing you to maintain a consistent configuration structure.</li>



<li><strong>Separation of Concerns:</strong> Keeping configuration settings in separate YAML or JSON files promotes the separation of concerns, making your codebase cleaner and more maintainable.</li>



<li><strong>Validation and Tooling:</strong> Various libraries and tools are available to validate and manage YAML or JSON configurations, helping you catch errors early in the development process.</li>
</ol>



<p>By integrating feature flagging and YAML or JSON tooling into your development workflow, you empower your engineering team to create highly configurable products. This approach not only enhances flexibility but also simplifies the process of managing and updating configurations for individual modular components and product features.</p>



<p>The combination of feature flagging and YAML or JSON tooling is a powerful strategy for building and managing configurable products efficiently. This approach enables controlled rollouts, conditional customization, and seamless configuration management, ultimately delivering a more adaptable and customer-centric product.</p>



<p>In conclusion, building configurable products is a strategic move that can lead to enhanced customer satisfaction, market adaptability, and cost efficiency. Shifting your team&#8217;s mindset towards configurability may take time and effort, but the benefits are well worth it. By following best practices and leveraging open source tools, you can lead your engineering team towards a more configurable and customer-centric future.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex"></figure>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/index.html">Configurability in Product Development: A Guide for Engineering Leaders</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Rutvik Bhatt</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../configurability-in-product-development-a-guide-for-engineering-leaders/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">5128</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

<!--
Performance optimized by W3 Total Cache. Learn more: https://www.boldgrid.com/w3-total-cache/

Object Caching 47/54 objects using disk
Page Caching using disk 
Content Delivery Network via N/A
Minified using disk
Database Caching 5/17 queries in 0.005 seconds using disk

Served from: rutvikbhatt.com @ 2023-10-07 16:36:40 by W3 Total Cache
-->